<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://asboyer.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://asboyer.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-17T22:32:50+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">asboyer.com</title><subtitle>Hi, I&apos;m Andrew Boyer and this is my personal website, asboyer.com. Here you can find more about what I’m up to and what I find interesting. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Sierra Escape, Part 1</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/the-sierra-escape-pt-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Sierra Escape, Part 1"/><published>2024-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/the-sierra-escape-pt-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/the-sierra-escape-pt-1/"><![CDATA[<style>#markdown-content{line-height:2.0!important}</style> <h2 style="text-align: center; margin-top: 30px">Prologue</h2> <p>          A lone vehicle pierced through the mountain fog. Albert Boyd had been driving all day and into the night. It had been ages since he’d seen another car. <em>Twelve hours and 14 minutes until arrival,</em> his GPS read. Albert sighed and squinted at the winding, narrow road ahead of him. He was overcome with another sense of drowsiness. Shivering, he shook himself awake. He had to be alert, his job was too important. Looking over his shoulder, Albert checked on his only passenger. Even though his limbs were chained to the back of the armored transport vehicle and a black bag covered his face, the prisoner appeared to be comfortably asleep. Albert shook his head in amusement and turned back to face the road. He’d been given no information about his passenger, who hadn’t said a word the entire drive. With only the instructions to keep a low profile while delivering the person of interest to the capital, Albert continued driving ahead, fighting fatigue and the temptation to stop. Hours passed like this. The road’s rhythmic turns were soothing. After battling sleep for the hundredth time, Albert gave in and slowly shut his eyes.</p> <h2 style="text-align: center; margin-top: 30px">Chapter 1</h2> <p>          <em>BANG!</em><br/>           The gun shot rang loud and echoed through the mountains. Dusty Hunter lowered his rifle and observed the kill. The slain bison lay in the tall grass nearby the creek. Maneuvering over to the fallen prey, careful not to disturb any other animals, Dusty drew his trusty hunting knife. Arriving at the kill sight, he respectfully shut the bison’s eyes before skillfully carving out the precious meat and packing it in his bag. He repeated the process, working his way around and up the base of the mountain, toward his cabin. It was usually hard to find bison up by his cabin, so it was a special treat when Dusty made his way down the mountain. Dusty looked to the sky and the sun shined down on him. He took a deep breath of the morning air and smiled, satisfied with today’s hunt. He checked his watch and it wasn’t even 8AM yet. Dusty turned and headed up the mountain to his cabin to cook some breakfast.<br/>           Every hunt, Dusty took the same trail back home. However, for whatever reason, whether it was his good mood or the crisp weather, Dusty decided to take the longer trail, the trail he would usually take on his scenic walks. It would pass by a tall cliff, which Dusty had always wanted to climb. For the eight or so months he had been living up here, he had yet to explore this particular cliff. The ledge on top intrigued him. <em>Was there another trail up there? It would be a great spot to build another cabin.</em> Dusty always took a few moments to ponder what was on the ledge every time he passed by, but he never took the time to scale the cliff. Dusty started on the trail, anticipating spotting the cliff, which was about a third of the way along the trail. As he crossed the brook with the thin stones, Dusty stopped in his tracks. In the distance, he saw a black cloud of smoke.<br/>           The entire eight and a half months he had been living in these mountains, Dusty hadn’t seen a single person. The population scarcity was one of the key reasons he picked this area to build his cabin. Dusty preferred isolation; he liked to believe that it was just him up here in the mountains with nature, nobody else. Yet, the very human part of his brain that craved social interaction moved his legs forward to the distant smoke.<br/>           As Dusty drew closer, he arrived at the clearing where the cliff was. Only this time, it wasn’t the cliff that captured his attention. At the base of the cliff was a damaged vehicle, front completely crushed, engine giving off the dark smoke he had seen before. Standing in the clearing, nearly in shock, Dusty traced the possible direction the large car could have come from. In these woods, there was only one possibility: the cliff. <em>There must be a road up on the ledge. That’s it. That’s what it is.</em><br/>           Before Dusty could feel any sense of triumph for discovering the secret of the ledge, he heard a crackle. A bush squashed under the damaged vehicle had begun to catch fire. Dusty acted quickly, dashing towards the wreckage, stomping out the flame, and cutting away any greenery that could catch flames from the smoldering engine. Relieved he alleviated the threat of fire to his precious woods, Dusty took a step back to inspect the damaged vehicle. Upon further inspection, he realized this was no ordinary vehicle. _This thing is armored._ Besides the crushed front, most of the vehicle remained intact, with a few ding marks here and there. As Dusty traversed to the front of the vehicle, a piece of black fabric caught his boot. He picked it up, noting it to be a hood of some sort, and tucked it into his back pocket.</p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>To be continued...</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="short-stories"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="sierra-escape"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first part of a new series]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Politics of Social Media Algorithms</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/social-media-ethics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Politics of Social Media Algorithms"/><published>2024-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/social-media-ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/social-media-ethics/"><![CDATA[<p>In the 21st century, social media algorithms control the flow of much of the world’s information and social connection. And while we have never been more digitally connected as a civilization, it is important to consider the underlying technology behind what drives these connections. Who controls what we see on social media? Why are we recommended certain content? For many people, their world view and perspective is at the mercy of their social media feed and thus the algorithms that have populated it. What consequences are intentional and what are unintentional, and how does this impact the different groups affected by this technology? We will explore all of these questions in this assignment.</p> <p>In his journal article, Langdon Winner defines politics as “arrangements of power and authority in human associations as well as the activities that take place within those arrangements” <a class="citation" href="#Winner1980">(Winner, 1980)</a>. Examining social media algorithms through this definition, we can classify them as highly political. The control over content distribution aligns with Winner’s concept of arrangements of power. And this power is wielded to impose specific values onto their users. The main value that social media algorithms embody is profit maximization, which in turn is driven by engagement and attention. And over the years, social media companies have optimized the algorithm to drive as much attention as they can to their platforms. Joanna Stern encapsulates this evolution in her article, saying “bye-bye, feeds that showed everything and everyone we followed in an unending, chronologically ordered river. Hello, high-energy feeds that popped with must-clicks” <a class="citation" href="#Stern2021">(Stern, 2021)</a>. This makes a lot of sense when you consider the motivations and politics of those driving these changes. For social media companies, the more engaging their platforms are, the more ads they can sell. “No algorithms, no ads” <a class="citation" href="#Stern2021">(Stern, 2021)</a>.</p> <p>It is one thing to create an engaging feed. It’s another to have a completely personalized and individual feed for each user, fine-tuned to retain that user for as long as possible. How is it that these algorithms can almost read our minds? Ben Smith investigated this in his article about TikTok, in which he found internal company documents that detail this elaborate system. These documents illustrate that “for each video a kid watches, TikTok gains a piece of information on him. In a few hours, the algorithm can detect his musical tastes, his physical attraction, if he’s depressed, if he might be into drugs, and many other sensitive information. There’s a high risk that some of this information will be used against him. It could potentially be used to micro-target him or make him more addicted to the platform” <a class="citation" href="#Smith2021">(Smith, 2021)</a>. TikTok also outlines their creator monetization program, in which they pay creators based on certain metrics, such as “likes, comments and playtime, as well as an indication that the video has been played” <a class="citation" href="#Smith2021">(Smith, 2021)</a>. Creators are rewarded for engagement and attention, which furthers the profit maximization value that social media algorithms embody.</p> <p>All things considered, it’s clear that companies intentionally make their apps addictive and they can control how their algorithms work. However, they have (or claim to have) very little control over what content is actually used to engage users and the impact that content has. For example, Horwitz and Blunt of the Wall Street Journal explored Instagram Reels and tested the content and advertisements they were shown after following select accounts. “The Journal reporters set up the Instagram test accounts as adults on newly purchased devices and followed the gymnasts, cheerleaders and other young influencers. The tests showed that following only the young girls triggered Instagram to begin serving videos from accounts promoting adult sex content alongside ads for major consumer brands, such as one for Walmart that ran after a video of a woman exposing her crotch” <a class="citation" href="#HorwitzBlunt2023">(Horwitz &amp; Blunt, 2023)</a>. Did Walmart intentionally choose to place their ads after this type of content? Did Instagram intentionally show this kind of content to this type of user? To both answers, most likely no. But there also is no doubt these algorithms have grown beyond any one person’s control. “When the test accounts then followed some users who followed those same young people’s accounts, they yielded even more disturbing recommendations. The platform served a mix of adult pornography and child-sexualizing material, such as a video of a clothed girl caressing her torso and another of a child pantomiming a sex act” <a class="citation" href="#HorwitzBlunt2023">(Horwitz &amp; Blunt, 2023)</a>. The hypothesis of the reporters was that Instagram’s “behavioral tracking has discerned that some Instagram users following preteen girls will want to engage with videos sexualizing children, and then directs such content toward them” <a class="citation" href="#HorwitzBlunt2023">(Horwitz &amp; Blunt, 2023)</a>. While social media algorithms are intentionally addictive, the type of content used to drive this addiction can oftentimes be unintentional.</p> <p>The alarming consequences of these unintentional effects have become apparent. As the algorithms prioritize content with high shock value, be it misinformation or sexually explicit material, and users influence the direction of such content, creators perpetuate the cycle by producing content that aligns with these preferences. While this vicious cycle of social media algorithms affect users and creators alike, children and adolescents using social media are one of the most impacted groups. Junior Senator Chris Murphy states that now more than ever, impressionable children have relinquished “their online autonomy so fully to their phones that they even balk at the idea of searching the internet — for them, the only acceptable online environment is one customized by big tech algorithms, which feed them customized content” <a class="citation" href="#Murphy2023">(Murphy, 2023)</a>. Murphy emphasizes that an unregulated access to social media algorithms has hurt the mental health and overall well-being of millions of kids. Whether it’s intentional or not, there are major implications for young kids affected by social media algorithms.</p> <p>In the end, the extensive influence of social media algorithms, driven by profit motives and engagement metrics, is highly political. These algorithms, designed to capture attention and maximize revenue, shape the information landscape and wield significant power over users’ experience. Recognizing the nature of this technology is essential for creating a digital environment that prioritizes transparency, ethics, and the well-being of users.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="school"/><category term="social-media"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CS 3001 Spring 2024 Assignment 2]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ethics of the Boeing Groundings</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/boeing-groundings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ethics of the Boeing Groundings"/><published>2024-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/boeing-groundings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/boeing-groundings/"><![CDATA[<p>As Boeing pushed for dominance in the airplane market, their engineering team made critical errors that greatly compromised the integrity and safety of their plane. The consequences? 346 lives. In this assignment, I will explore what went wrong and how these key errors compare to other engineering mistakes that have led to tragic deaths. Through these cases, we can learn how overconfidence in software, failure to eliminate root causes, and inadequate investigation can all lead to deadly software bugs.</p> <p>Boeing was (and still is) one of two major titans in the aircraft manufacturing market <a class="citation" href="#aviationweek2015">(Aviation Week Network, 2015)</a>. However, the other major player in the industry, Airbus, had been rolling out a major update to their flagship plane, the A320. This update had been in the works since 2010 and its biggest feature would be a new turbo-fan engine that was more fuel efficient, saving airlines major costs. This major shift in the market was felt by Boeing, who began rolling out their own updated plane, the 737 Max <a class="citation" href="#mouawad2010">(Mouawad, 2010)</a>. There was one important detail, however. Boeing’s plane was lower to the ground than the Airbus plane. Adding a bigger engine to the 737 would cause more problems than it did for the A320. Yet, even though Boeing executives had previously said they wouldn’t re-engine the 737, in 2011 production head Mike Bair stated that his team had found a way to fit the engine under the wing <a class="citation" href="#leeham2019">(Leeham News and Analysis, 2019)</a>. Their solution was to simply move the engine higher on the wing. Boeing’s new plane saved the company from losing exclusive airline deals to Airbus <a class="citation" href="#gelles2019">(Gelles et al., 2019)</a>. Unfortunately, the change to engine position had unintended consequences. When at full thrust, the nose pointed too far upward. Boeing’s solution was MCAS (Maneuvering characteristics augmentation system). A sensor in the front of the plane would detect oncoming airflow, and this data was collected and sent to the flight computer. If the angle was too high, MCAS activated and lifted the plane’s tail upward to move the nose downward <a class="citation" href="#gates2019">(Gates &amp; Baker, 2019)</a>.</p> <div class="profile float-right"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/737-max-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/737-max-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/737-max-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="(min-width: 800px) 577.5px, (min-width: 576px) 40vw, 95vw"" type="image/webp"> <img src="/assets/img/blog/737-max.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1 rounded" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The 737 Max</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>The problem here laid in the fact that this feature was not communicated to the public, especially pilots. So in 2018, when the plane began lurching downward on the Lion Air Flight, pilots had no idea why. As they frantically searched the manual and fought with MCAS, the plane continued to nose dive. Eventually, this led to a crash and a death toll of 189. Flight reports demonstrated evidence that the MCAS failed because of incorrect sensor data <a class="citation" href="#bellamy2019">(Bellamy, 2019)</a>. The 2019 Ethiopian crash was similar, but pilots disabled the MCAS. Still, the plane was already in full nose dive at this time, too late to regain control. The crash killed 157 people <a class="citation" href="#kitroeff2019ethiopian">(Kitroeff et al., 2019)</a>.</p> <p>While these crashes were devastating, in the past we have seen similar situations where bad engineering practices have endangered and taken human lives. The Therac-25 deaths were a similar situation and the lessons learned in that investigation are also relevant to the Boeing crashes. In Nancy Leveson’s analysis of the Therac-25 accidents, she identifies “causal factors” that can be learned from these engineering mistakes <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>.</p> <div class="row justify-content-md-center"> <div class="col-md-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/mcas-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/mcas-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/mcas-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/mcas.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Left Aligned Image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption">How MCAS worked.</div> </div> </div> <p>The first of these factors is overconfidence in software. In both cases, a general overconfidence in software played a significant role in the accidents. In Boeing’s case, the use of a single sensor was considered acceptable because engineers “calculated the probability of a ‘hazardous’ MCAS malfunction to be virtually inconceivable” <a class="citation" href="#gates2019">(Gates &amp; Baker, 2019)</a>. Unfortunately, the MCAS was at the mercy of its sensor, which Lion Airlines plane had replaced just two days prior to the crash <a class="citation" href="#bellamy2019">(Bellamy, 2019)</a>. Not only did this overconfidence lead to the bug, but also to the lack of transparency among pilots. Boeing was so sure the MCAS was error proof that the 737 Max was marketed as nearly identical to its predecessor <a class="citation" href="#kitroeff2019training">(Kitroeff et al., 2019)</a>. This led to a severe lack of mandated additional training for pilots flying the 737 Max for the first time. Those who flew the plane were told that it was nearly identical to previous models and were given a handbook and a two-hour iPad course as training, which had no mention of the MCAS <a class="citation" href="#kitroeff2019training">(Kitroeff et al., 2019)</a>. Boeing assumed that pilots could handle MCAS-related issues without any information about the actual MCAS. The Therac-25 situation was similar; overconfidence in software also led to deaths in this case. Early safety analysis of the Therac-25 didn’t even test the software and any problems were written off as mistakes in the hardware <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>. Additionally, very little software features were actually communicated to those operating the machine, leaving them completely in the dark when errors began to ensue. While Boeing was confident in their new software and for Therac-25 the reused software, both situations show the assumption that the average operator can understand confusing software is inherently flawed.</p> <p>Secondly, in both situations, there was a clear failure to eliminate root causes. In the case of the 737 Max, rather than completely redesigning the plane to fit a bigger engine, Boeing thought they could design a simple workaround, completely reliant on software. The root cause was the change in engine position, which led to side effects, including the nose pointing more upward than it should have been during full throttle. This side effect was not harmless, potentially leading to an engine stall mid-flight. Rather than eliminating the root cause, Boeing came up with a workaround: the MCAS <a class="citation" href="#gelles2019">(Gelles et al., 2019)</a>. Leveson states that in the case of the Therac-25, and similar situations, “focusing on particular software design errors is not the way to make a system safe. Virtually all complex software can be made to behave in an unexpected fashion under some conditions. There will always be another software bug” <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>. Her point is that while software errors will always occur, we can mitigate these effects by including hardware failsafes. While the Therac-25 incidents involved software reuse at the root cause, Boeing’s root cause was a design flaw resulting from the decision to fit a larger engine into an existing aircraft structure. However, in both cases, the 737 Max and Therac-25 lacked failsafes and relied on software to patch the root causes of the potentially deadly issues.</p> <div class="profile float-right"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/therac-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/therac-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/therac-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="(min-width: 800px) 231.0px, (min-width: 576px) 30vw, 95vw"" type="image/webp"> <img src="/assets/img/blog/therac.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1 rounded" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Paitent with the Therac-25</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>Finally, both cases conducted inadequate investigations when following up on accident reports. In 2018, several pilots complained the 737 Max nosing downward during flight <a class="citation" href="#aspinwall2019">(Aspinwall et al., 2019)</a>. Records show that one captain said it was “unconscionable” that pilots were allowed to fly the plane “without adequate training or fully disclosing information about how its systems were different from those on previous 737 models” <a class="citation" href="#aspinwall2019">(Aspinwall et al., 2019)</a>. This was just months before the Ethiopian Air crash. Even after the Lion Air crash, Boeing and the federal government failed to identify (or disclose) what had actually caused the crash, endangering even more lives and leading to another crash. Looking at the Therac-25, Levenson states that “the first phone call by Tim Still should have led to an extensive investigation of the events at Kennestone. Certainly, learning about the first lawsuit should have triggered an immediate response” <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>. While the weight of the situation and death toll differs from case to case, it’s clear that the companies should have taken heed to the early warnings and incidents that occurred. Instead, they waited until the problem became so big they couldn’t file it away. Paying close attention to previous errors and complaints could have saved lives if adequate investigations had been conducted.</p> <p>In the end, we can learn a lot from the Boeing 737 Max crashes, as well as other incidents like the Therac-25. If we can eliminate these key “causal factors” <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a> and adhere to safe and ethical engineering practices, we can prevent senseless deaths and tragedies.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="school"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CS 3001 Spring 2024 Assignment 1]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">“When Kobe Bryant died, a piece of me died.”</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2023/jordan-speech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“When Kobe Bryant died, a piece of me died.”"/><published>2023-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2023/jordan-speech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2023/jordan-speech/"><![CDATA[<p>Michael Jordan’s heartfelt speech at Kobe Bryant’s memorial honored the late star’s life and legacy, while also providing comfort and solace to others mourning Kobe’s tragic and unexpected passing. Through sharing his own insight, emotion, and experiences with Kobe, Jordan builds an effective argument regarding the importance of passion and living in the moment. His speech is a powerful tribute to Bryant and serves to encourage the audience to emulate the fallen icon’s tireless work ethic and spirit. Jordan effectively uses rhetorical techniques and appeals to accomplish his purpose of eulogizing his “little brother” and inspiring anyone listening.</p> <p>Michael Jordan is a legend, widely regarded as the greatest basketball player of all time. Six-time NBA champion, four-time olympic gold medalist, and five-time league MVP are just a select few of his many accolades. During his career he reached a level of global recognition and fame that almost no other athlete has ever garnered. Yet, Jordan has addressed the public only a handful of times since his (final) retirement in 2003. His infrequent public appearances make this particular eulogy all the more special. While his fellow NBA legends and celebrities in attendance wish they were hearing from him on a better occasion, Jordan’s tribute to Kobe is still highly anticipated. In addition to Kobe’s friends, family, and fans in the live audience, the broader basketball community all around the world tune in online to hear Jordan pay homage to Kobe.</p> <p>Jordan appeals to ethos to build trust with the audience and establish himself as a credible source on Kobe’s life and character. While Jordan has previously solidified his status within basketball many times over, this speech is about honoring Kobe and the legacy that he left behind. Jordan emphasizes the extent of his relationship with Kobe to build credibility within this new context. He recounts that “Kobe used to call me, text me, 11:30, 2:30, 3 o’clock in the morning. Talking about post up moves, footwork, and sometimes, the triangle.” Kobe was one of the world’s most famous and successful athletes: there are very few people that he’s calling for advice, especially at 3 AM. By telling this story, Jordan establishes his role as Kobe’s mentor. He can now give the unique perspective of someone that Kobe looked up to, someone who can attest to Kobe’s desire to improve, his mindset, and ultimately his accomplishments. Viewing Kobe from the lens of a proud mentor makes for a powerful eulogy and allows Jordan to share memories that many in the audience are not familiar with. Later in his speech, Jordan mentions his own family, saying “I have a daughter who is thirty, I just became a grandparent. And I have two twins at six.” This draws a congratulatory applause from the crowd but also further establishes Jordan’s credibility, this time as a parent. Now from his view as a father, Jordan effectively commemorates Kobe’s commitment to family life, saying “I am inspired by what he has done and what he has shared with Vanessa and what he’s shared with his kids.” Jordan humbly uses ethos to establish himself as Kobe’s mentor and someone that can personally attest to his success on and off the basketball court.</p> <p>Jordan’s use of appeals to pathos are the most noticeable of the rhetorical devices that he employs throughout his speech. And how could they not be? The passing of Kobe, his daughter, and the other victims in the helicopter crash was a devastating tragedy. The entire basketball community is reeling from the loss of a beloved icon. In response, Jordan uses an appropriate mix of heavy emotion and light humor to deeply connect with and draw emotion from the audience. Throughout his speech, Jordan fights through tears, like many in attendance. But as he continues, he smiles, telling stories that bring others to also smile through their own pain. He uses a few timely self-deprecating jokes, mentioning a conversation he and Kobe had about baseball, Jordan’s unsuccessful venture into a new sport. However, one of the most memorable moments of the entire memorial was Jordan, fighting tears, saying “now I’ll have to look at another crying meme for the next…” His words trail off as the crowd erupts in laughter and applause, alleviating the heavy emotional tension. In the audience, fans, Stephen Curry, and even Kobe’s wife Vanessa all share a smile. With this joke, Jordan is referencing his last memorable public speech, where he teared up while being inducted to the basketball hall of fame. Pictures of Jordan crying became a meme in sports culture for years. So amidst these heavy emotions, Jordan turns something embarrassing for him into a joke that becomes a pivotal moment in the speech. He ends his humorous appeal by turning the focus back to Kobe: “but that is what Kobe Bryant does to me. I’m pretty sure Vanessa and his friends could all say the same thing, he knows how to get to you in a way that affects you personally.” Jordan’s joke, followed by his touching reflection is a whirlwind of emotions powerful enough to deeply impact the audience.</p> <div class="row justify-content-md-center"> <div class="col-md-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/michael-jordan-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/michael-jordan-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/michael-jordan-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/michael-jordan.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Jordan delivers speech" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption">Jordan delivering his speech.</div> </div> </div> <p>Another appeal to pathos and a key point throughout his speech is Jordan’s description of Kobe Bryant as his “little brother.” His use of familial language in comparing his bond to Kobe as a brotherhood deeply resonates with the audience, further indicating the impact that Kobe had on him. One of Jordan’s most powerful appeals is when he relates to the audience through family, saying “all of us have brothers and sisters, little brothers, little sisters who, for whatever reason, always tend to get in your stuff, your closet, your shoes, everything. It was a nuisance. But that nuisance turned into love over a period of time. Just because of the admiration they have for you as big brothers or big sisters. The questions, the wanting to know every little detail about the life they were about to embark on.” This appeal draws multiple results. It relates to those who have siblings (literal or figurative), it uses some humor to diffuse the crowd’s grief (his emphasis on “nuisance” drew a laugh), and most importantly communicates Jordan’s love for Kobe and the sense of loss he feels at his passing. Jordan’s repetition of “little brother” and “big brother” carries through the speech and makes an emotional impact on anyone listening. Jordan uses this appeal to effectively communicate Kobe’s impact on him, saying “what Kobe Bryant was to me was the inspiration that somebody truly cared about the way I played the game or the way that he wanted to play the game. He wanted to be the best basketball player he could be. And as I got to know him, I wanted to be the best big brother I could be.” Jordan’s use of familial language to illustrate the brotherhood he and Kobe shared is one of the most potent and effective appeals in his speech.</p> <div class="profile float-right"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/kobe-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/kobe-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/kobe-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="(min-width: 800px) 577.5px, (min-width: 576px) 40vw, 95vw"" type="image/webp"> <img src="/assets/img/blog/kobe.jpeg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1 rounded" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Kobe Bryant</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>Although Jordan’s speech is an emotional eulogy, he still uses subtle elements that appeal to logos and reason. Throughout, he personally attests to Kobe’s character, using anecdotes as evidence. Jordan speaks about visiting Phil Jackson, his former and Kobe’s current (at the time) coach. “I saw Phil Jackson in 1999… and I walk in and Kobe’s sitting there. And I’m in a suit. The first thing Kobe said: ‘Did you bring your shoes?’” This small recount from Jordan is a specific example of the competitive spirit Kobe had that Jordan admired him for. Jordan uses this same technique again to showcase Kobe’s dedication as a father: “I remember a couple of months ago he sends me a text and he said ‘I’m trying to teach my daughter some moves…what were you thinking about as you were trying to work on your moves?’” By telling this story, Jordan gives clear evidence that proves Kobe’s commitment to family. It’s one thing to say he was a great father; Jordan takes it a step further by showing he was a great father. Many of the quick anecdotes Jordan shares throughout his speech not only provide specific instances of Kobe’s high character, but also inspire the audience by giving clear evidence of what Kobe stood for. Jordan uses logos successfully throughout his speech, leaving the audience with no questions about the kind of athlete, man, and father Kobe was.</p> <p>Jordan both begins and ends his speech by effectively appealing to kairos, emphasizing the urgency and importance of living in the present moment. In Jordan’s opening remarks he says, “in the game of basketball, in life, as a parent, Kobe left nothing in the tank. He left it all on the floor.” He repeats this sentiment throughout his speech, saying “Kobe gave every last ounce of himself to whatever he was doing.” Referencing Kobe’s unrelenting spirit and attitude towards life, Jordan calls on the audience to take inspiration from Kobe’s example and live with the same intensity. Finally, Jordan closes his speech with a specific call to action. “Kobe never left anything on the court. And I think that’s what he would want us to do. No one knows how much time we have. That is why we must live in the moment, we must enjoy the moment, we must reach, and see, and spend as much time as we can with our families and friends and the people that we absolutely love.” Jordan’s dual appeal to kairos is so powerful because it speaks to both what Kobe would have wanted and how to achieve it. Jordan emphasizes Kobe’s all-out approach to life throughout the speech, inspiring the audience to embody this same spirit. He further emphasizes the urgency of his message by reminding the audience that no one knows how much time they have, reinforcing the importance of making the most of every moment. Jordan’s specific call to action encourages the audience to be present in the moment and spend time with loved ones, making his message memorable as well as actionable. Ultimately, Jordan’s use of kairos in his speech honors Kobe’s memory while also inspiring and motivating the audience to live their lives to the fullest.</p> <p>Throughout his speech Jordan appeals to ethos, pathos, logos, and kairos to not only pay homage, but motivate the audience to live with the same passion for life as Kobe. Jordan left all those listening with an inspiring call to action, while also easing their grief through a mix of emotional display and humor. He establishes himself as a credible source on Kobe’s life and provides clear evidence to how Kobe succeeded on and off the court. While all of these appeals are effective in their own right, Jordan’s appeals to pathos stand out the most. He’s giving a eulogy after all. Jordan’s emotional appeals are strong and turn the horrible tragedy of Kobe’s death into a celebration of his life, while inspiring the audience at the same time. He displays his own pain while speaking through tears, yet still finds a way to use timely humor to ease the emotions of the crowd. And while establishing credibility, providing evidence, and creating urgency serves Jordan well throughout his speech, it wouldn’t be the touching eulogy that it is without his heartfelt appeals to pathos. In conclusion, Michael Jordan delivers a powerful and impactful speech at Kobe Bryant’s memorial service that effectively utilizes rhetorical appeals to craft an emotional and touching tribute to the late Laker legend.</p> <p><a class="citation" href="#jordan2020kobe">(Jordan, 2020)</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="basketball"/><category term="speech-analysis"/><category term="school"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ENG 105 Spring 2023 Writing Project 1]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting the NBA MVP with Python</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2022/python-mvp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting the NBA MVP with Python"/><published>2022-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2022/python-mvp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2022/python-mvp/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page…</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="projects"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="python"/><category term="basketball"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is how I built the first varation of Goat Grade]]></summary></entry></feed>