<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://asboyer.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://asboyer.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-02-06T09:08:35+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">asboyer.com</title><subtitle>Hi, I&apos;m Andrew Boyer and this is my personal website, asboyer.com. Here you can find more about what I’m up to and what I find interesting. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Politics of Social Media Algorithms</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/social-media-ethics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Politics of Social Media Algorithms"/><published>2024-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/social-media-ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/social-media-ethics/"><![CDATA[<p>In the 21st century, social media algorithms control the flow of much of the world’s information and social connection. And while we have never been more digitally connected as a civilization, it is important to consider the underlying technology behind what drives these connections. Who controls what we see on social media? Why are we recommended certain content? For many people, their world view and perspective is at the mercy of their social media feed and thus the algorithms that have populated it. What consequences are intentional and what are unintentional, and how does this impact the different groups affected by this technology? We will explore all of these questions in this assignment.</p> <p>In his journal article, Langdon Winner defines politics as “arrangements of power and authority in human associations as well as the activities that take place within those arrangements” <a class="citation" href="#Winner1980">(Winner, 1980)</a>. Examining social media algorithms through this definition, we can classify them as highly political. The control over content distribution aligns with Winner’s concept of arrangements of power. And this power is wielded to impose specific values onto their users. The main value that social media algorithms embody is profit maximization, which in turn is driven by engagement and attention. And over the years, social media companies have optimized the algorithm to drive as much attention as they can to their platforms. Joanna Stern encapsulates this evolution in her article, saying “bye-bye, feeds that showed everything and everyone we followed in an unending, chronologically ordered river. Hello, high-energy feeds that popped with must-clicks” <a class="citation" href="#Stern2021">(Stern, 2021)</a>. This makes a lot of sense when you consider the motivations and politics of those driving these changes. For social media companies, the more engaging their platforms are, the more ads they can sell. “No algorithms, no ads” <a class="citation" href="#Stern2021">(Stern, 2021)</a>.</p> <p>It is one thing to create an engaging feed. It’s another to have a completely personalized and individual feed for each user, fine-tuned to retain that user for as long as possible. How is it that these algorithms can almost read our minds? Ben Smith investigated this in his article about TikTok, in which he found internal company documents that detail this elaborate system. These documents illustrate that “for each video a kid watches, TikTok gains a piece of information on him. In a few hours, the algorithm can detect his musical tastes, his physical attraction, if he’s depressed, if he might be into drugs, and many other sensitive information. There’s a high risk that some of this information will be used against him. It could potentially be used to micro-target him or make him more addicted to the platform” <a class="citation" href="#Smith2021">(Smith, 2021)</a>. TikTok also outlines their creator monetization program, in which they pay creators based on certain metrics, such as “likes, comments and playtime, as well as an indication that the video has been played” <a class="citation" href="#Smith2021">(Smith, 2021)</a>. Creators are rewarded for engagement and attention, which furthers the profit maximization value that social media algorithms embody.</p> <p>All things considered, it’s clear that companies intentionally make their apps addictive and they can control how their algorithms work. However, they have (or claim to have) very little control over what content is actually used to engage users and the impact that content has. For example, Horwitz and Blunt of the Wall Street Journal explored Instagram Reels and tested the content and advertisements they were shown after following select accounts. “The Journal reporters set up the Instagram test accounts as adults on newly purchased devices and followed the gymnasts, cheerleaders and other young influencers. The tests showed that following only the young girls triggered Instagram to begin serving videos from accounts promoting adult sex content alongside ads for major consumer brands, such as one for Walmart that ran after a video of a woman exposing her crotch” <a class="citation" href="#HorwitzBlunt2023">(Horwitz &amp; Blunt, 2023)</a>. Did Walmart intentionally choose to place their ads after this type of content? Did Instagram intentionally show this kind of content to this type of user? To both answers, most likely no. But there also is no doubt these algorithms have grown beyond any one person’s control. “When the test accounts then followed some users who followed those same young people’s accounts, they yielded even more disturbing recommendations. The platform served a mix of adult pornography and child-sexualizing material, such as a video of a clothed girl caressing her torso and another of a child pantomiming a sex act” <a class="citation" href="#HorwitzBlunt2023">(Horwitz &amp; Blunt, 2023)</a>. The hypothesis of the reporters was that Instagram’s “behavioral tracking has discerned that some Instagram users following preteen girls will want to engage with videos sexualizing children, and then directs such content toward them” <a class="citation" href="#HorwitzBlunt2023">(Horwitz &amp; Blunt, 2023)</a>. While social media algorithms are intentionally addictive, the type of content used to drive this addiction can oftentimes be unintentional.</p> <p>The alarming consequences of these unintentional effects have become apparent. As the algorithms prioritize content with high shock value, be it misinformation or sexually explicit material, and users influence the direction of such content, creators perpetuate the cycle by producing content that aligns with these preferences. While this vicious cycle of social media algorithms affect users and creators alike, children and adolescents using social media are one of the most impacted groups. Junior Senator Chris Murphy states that now more than ever, impressionable children have relinquished “their online autonomy so fully to their phones that they even balk at the idea of searching the internet — for them, the only acceptable online environment is one customized by big tech algorithms, which feed them customized content” <a class="citation" href="#Murphy2023">(Murphy, 2023)</a>. Murphy emphasizes that an unregulated access to social media algorithms has hurt the mental health and overall well-being of millions of kids. Whether it’s intentional or not, there are major implications for young kids affected by social media algorithms.</p> <p>In the end, the extensive influence of social media algorithms, driven by profit motives and engagement metrics, is highly political. These algorithms, designed to capture attention and maximize revenue, shape the information landscape and wield significant power over users’ experience. Recognizing the nature of this technology is essential for creating a digital environment that prioritizes transparency, ethics, and the well-being of users.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="school"/><category term="social-media"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CS 3001 Spring 2024 Assignment 2]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ethics of the Boeing Groundings</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/boeing-groundings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ethics of the Boeing Groundings"/><published>2024-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/boeing-groundings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2024/boeing-groundings/"><![CDATA[<p>As Boeing pushed for dominance in the airplane market, their engineering team made critical errors that greatly compromised the integrity and safety of their plane. The consequences? 346 lives. In this assignment, I will explore what went wrong and how these key errors compare to other engineering mistakes that have led to tragic deaths. Through these cases, we can learn how overconfidence in software, failure to eliminate root causes, and inadequate investigation can all lead to deadly software bugs.</p> <p>Boeing was (and still is) one of two major titans in the aircraft manufacturing market <a class="citation" href="#aviationweek2015">(Aviation Week Network, 2015)</a>. However, the other major player in the industry, Airbus, had been rolling out a major update to their flagship plane, the A320. This update had been in the works since 2010 and its biggest feature would be a new turbo-fan engine that was more fuel efficient, saving airlines major costs. This major shift in the market was felt by Boeing, who began rolling out their own updated plane, the 737 Max <a class="citation" href="#mouawad2010">(Mouawad, 2010)</a>. There was one important detail, however. Boeing’s plane was lower to the ground than the Airbus plane. Adding a bigger engine to the 737 would cause more problems than it did for the A320. Yet, even though Boeing executives had previously said they wouldn’t re-engine the 737, in 2011 production head Mike Bair stated that his team had found a way to fit the engine under the wing <a class="citation" href="#leeham2019">(Leeham News and Analysis, 2019)</a>. Their solution was to simply move the engine higher on the wing. Boeing’s new plane saved the company from losing exclusive airline deals to Airbus <a class="citation" href="#gelles2019">(Gelles et al., 2019)</a>. Unfortunately, the change to engine position had unintended consequences. When at full thrust, the nose pointed too far upward. Boeing’s solution was MCAS (Maneuvering characteristics augmentation system). A sensor in the front of the plane would detect oncoming airflow, and this data was collected and sent to the flight computer. If the angle was too high, MCAS activated and lifted the plane’s tail upward to move the nose downward <a class="citation" href="#gates2019">(Gates &amp; Baker, 2019)</a>.</p> <div class="profile float-right"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/737-max-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/737-max-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/737-max-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="(min-width: 800px) 577.5px, (min-width: 576px) 40vw, 95vw"" type="image/webp"> <img src="/assets/img/blog/737-max.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1 rounded" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">The 737 Max</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>The problem here laid in the fact that this feature was not communicated to the public, especially pilots. So in 2018, when the plane began lurching downward on the Lion Air Flight, pilots had no idea why. As they frantically searched the manual and fought with MCAS, the plane continued to nose dive. Eventually, this led to a crash and a death toll of 189. Flight reports demonstrated evidence that the MCAS failed because of incorrect sensor data <a class="citation" href="#bellamy2019">(Bellamy, 2019)</a>. The 2019 Ethiopian crash was similar, but pilots disabled the MCAS. Still, the plane was already in full nose dive at this time, too late to regain control. The crash killed 157 people <a class="citation" href="#kitroeff2019ethiopian">(Kitroeff et al., 2019)</a>.</p> <p>While these crashes were devastating, in the past we have seen similar situations where bad engineering practices have endangered and taken human lives. The Therac-25 deaths were a similar situation and the lessons learned in that investigation are also relevant to the Boeing crashes. In Nancy Leveson’s analysis of the Therac-25 accidents, she identifies “causal factors” that can be learned from these engineering mistakes <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>.</p> <div class="row justify-content-md-center"> <div class="col-md-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/mcas-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/mcas-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/mcas-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/mcas.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="Left Aligned Image" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption">How MCAS worked.</div> </div> </div> <p>The first of these factors is overconfidence in software. In both cases, a general overconfidence in software played a significant role in the accidents. In Boeing’s case, the use of a single sensor was considered acceptable because engineers “calculated the probability of a ‘hazardous’ MCAS malfunction to be virtually inconceivable” <a class="citation" href="#gates2019">(Gates &amp; Baker, 2019)</a>. Unfortunately, the MCAS was at the mercy of its sensor, which Lion Airlines plane had replaced just two days prior to the crash <a class="citation" href="#bellamy2019">(Bellamy, 2019)</a>. Not only did this overconfidence lead to the bug, but also to the lack of transparency among pilots. Boeing was so sure the MCAS was error proof that the 737 Max was marketed as nearly identical to its predecessor <a class="citation" href="#kitroeff2019training">(Kitroeff et al., 2019)</a>. This led to a severe lack of mandated additional training for pilots flying the 737 Max for the first time. Those who flew the plane were told that it was nearly identical to previous models and were given a handbook and a two-hour iPad course as training, which had no mention of the MCAS <a class="citation" href="#kitroeff2019training">(Kitroeff et al., 2019)</a>. Boeing assumed that pilots could handle MCAS-related issues without any information about the actual MCAS. The Therac-25 situation was similar; overconfidence in software also led to deaths in this case. Early safety analysis of the Therac-25 didn’t even test the software and any problems were written off as mistakes in the hardware <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>. Additionally, very little software features were actually communicated to those operating the machine, leaving them completely in the dark when errors began to ensue. While Boeing was confident in their new software and for Therac-25 the reused software, both situations show the assumption that the average operator can understand confusing software is inherently flawed.</p> <p>Secondly, in both situations, there was a clear failure to eliminate root causes. In the case of the 737 Max, rather than completely redesigning the plane to fit a bigger engine, Boeing thought they could design a simple workaround, completely reliant on software. The root cause was the change in engine position, which led to side effects, including the nose pointing more upward than it should have been during full throttle. This side effect was not harmless, potentially leading to an engine stall mid-flight. Rather than eliminating the root cause, Boeing came up with a workaround: the MCAS <a class="citation" href="#gelles2019">(Gelles et al., 2019)</a>. Leveson states that in the case of the Therac-25, and similar situations, “focusing on particular software design errors is not the way to make a system safe. Virtually all complex software can be made to behave in an unexpected fashion under some conditions. There will always be another software bug” <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>. Her point is that while software errors will always occur, we can mitigate these effects by including hardware failsafes. While the Therac-25 incidents involved software reuse at the root cause, Boeing’s root cause was a design flaw resulting from the decision to fit a larger engine into an existing aircraft structure. However, in both cases, the 737 Max and Therac-25 lacked failsafes and relied on software to patch the root causes of the potentially deadly issues.</p> <div class="profile float-right"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/therac-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/therac-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/therac-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="(min-width: 800px) 231.0px, (min-width: 576px) 30vw, 95vw"" type="image/webp"> <img src="/assets/img/blog/therac.jpg" class="img-fluid z-depth-1 rounded" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Paitent with the Therac-25</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p>Finally, both cases conducted inadequate investigations when following up on accident reports. In 2018, several pilots complained the 737 Max nosing downward during flight <a class="citation" href="#aspinwall2019">(Aspinwall et al., 2019)</a>. Records show that one captain said it was “unconscionable” that pilots were allowed to fly the plane “without adequate training or fully disclosing information about how its systems were different from those on previous 737 models” <a class="citation" href="#aspinwall2019">(Aspinwall et al., 2019)</a>. This was just months before the Ethiopian Air crash. Even after the Lion Air crash, Boeing and the federal government failed to identify (or disclose) what had actually caused the crash, endangering even more lives and leading to another crash. Looking at the Therac-25, Levenson states that “the first phone call by Tim Still should have led to an extensive investigation of the events at Kennestone. Certainly, learning about the first lawsuit should have triggered an immediate response” <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a>. While the weight of the situation and death toll differs from case to case, it’s clear that the companies should have taken heed to the early warnings and incidents that occurred. Instead, they waited until the problem became so big they couldn’t file it away. Paying close attention to previous errors and complaints could have saved lives if adequate investigations had been conducted.</p> <p>In the end, we can learn a lot from the Boeing 737 Max crashes, as well as other incidents like the Therac-25. If we can eliminate these key “causal factors” <a class="citation" href="#levenson1995">(Levenson, 1995)</a> and adhere to safe and ethical engineering practices, we can prevent senseless deaths and tragedies.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="school"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CS 3001 Spring 2024 Assignment 1]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting the NBA MVP with Python</title><link href="https://asboyer.com/blog/2022/redirect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting the NBA MVP with Python"/><published>2022-02-07T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-07T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://asboyer.com/blog/2022/redirect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://asboyer.com/blog/2022/redirect/"><![CDATA[<p>Redirecting to another page…</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Boyer</name></author><category term="projects"/><category term="andrew-boyer"/><category term="python"/><category term="basketball"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is how I built the first varation of Goat Grade]]></summary></entry></feed>